Providence & Worcester Railroad Records 1997.0120
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Providence & Worcester Railroad Records
undated, 1826-1997
1997.0120
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
156.1 Linear feet
The records consist of administrative, financial, and real estate documents associated with the Providence & Worcestor Railroad, a railroad in eastern Connecticut, Rhode Island, and southern Massachusetts, founded in 1844 and leased by the New York & New England Railroad and subsequently the New Haven Railroad in the late 19th century. The company was part of the transfer of railroads to Penn Central in 1969 but resumed running as an independent line in 1973. The records also include small sets of records of the Norwich & Worcester Railroad, the Moshassuck Valley Railroad and the American Short Line Association.
Providence & Worcester Railroad.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the railroads of southern New England. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Provenance and Acquisition
The records were donated by the Providence & Worcester Railroad prior to 1997.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Scope and Content
The records consist of administrative, financial, and real estate documents associated with the Providence & Worcestor Railroad in its early phase prior to it being leased and absorbed by the New York & New England Railroad and the New Haven Railroad, through the 20th century while under lease to the New Haven Railroad, and the time after 1973 when it separated from Penn Central and resumed running as an independent rail line. The records also include small sets of records of the Norwich & Worcester Railroad, the Moshassuck Valley Railroad and the American Short Line Association.
Series I consists of records of the Providence & Worcestor Railroad generated while it was an independent railroad in the 19th century and includes many documents associated with the railroad line even after it was leased by the New York & New England Railroad and the New Haven Railroad. The records include correspondence and bonds of the President's Office, correspondence, accounts, cash books, cash balance ledgers, lists of stockholders and dividends ledgers of the Treasurer's Office, and letters and reports generated by the Superindendent's Office.
Series II consists of records mostly generated after the company became independent in 1973, consisting of stockholder's documents and stock transfer journals.
Series III holds records associated with the Norwich & Worcestor Railroad representing the company throughout its history, and consist of President's Office records, stockholder reports and correspondence, and information about accidents, agreements, insurance, patents, by-laws, mortgages, and other topics.
Series IV has a small number of records of the Moshassuck Valley Railroad after it was absorbed into the Providence & Worcester Railroad.
Series V consists of documents generated by the Providence & Worcester Railroad's connection to the American Short Line Railroad Association, consisting of annual meeting proceedings, newsletters, correspondence and traffic bulletins.
Series VI consists of real estate documents generated by the P&W and the N&W, combined and accessible by state and thereunder by town where the land was located. The series includes many documents from and to the Interstate Commerce Commission about the valuation of property owned by the railroad lines and schedules of title. Other documents include appraisals, records of land changes, reports to the ICC, and roadway completion reports.
Series VII consists of valuation and other maps of property of the P&W and N&W.
Organizational history
The Providence & Worcestor Railroad was incorporated in Massachusetts as the Providence and Worcester Railway on March 12, 1844, and as the Providence and Worcester Railroad in Rhode Island in May 1844. The two companies merged November 25, 1845, as the Providence and Worcester Railroad. The company bought the Blackstone Canal, also running between Providence, Rhode Island, and Worcester, Massachusetts, and began construction, partly on its banks, in 1845. The line opened in two sections, the part south of Millville on September 27, 1847, and the rest on October 20. The line from Providence to Central Falls, Rhode Island, was shared with the Boston and Providence Railroad, which at the same time built a connection from its old line (ending in East Providence) over to the Providence & Worcester Railroad.
In 1889 the Providence &Worcester Railroad was leased to the New York, Providence & Boston Railroad. On July 1, 1892, the New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad, better known as the New Haven Railroad, assumed that lease for 99 years. The New Haven Railroad merged into Penn Central on January 1, 1969. On April 6, 1970, the P&W announced its intention to separate from the merger. After a legal battle, the Interstate Commerce Commission approved the request on August 25, 1972, and on November 2 Penn Central signed the agreement effective December 30. The P&W cancelled the lease on February 3, 1973. Since then, the P&W has taken over many other lines from the former Penn Central and Boston and Maine Railroad and acquired trackage rights over Amtrak's shore line west of Providence. By the mid-1980s it owned over 400 miles of track in Connecticut, Rhode Island and Massachusetts.
The Norwich & Worcester Railroad was chartered in 1832 as the Boston, Norwich & New London Railroad but was consolidated in 1836 as the Norwich & Worcester Railroad. Service began on the route in 1839 and formed part of a through route between Boston and New York City. In 1843 tracks were extended six miles south from Norwich to Allyn's Point in Connecticut so that steamships could dock in ice-free waters on the Thames River during the winters. In 1869 the N&W was leased to the New York & New England Railroad, and then became part of the New Haven Railroad system in 1898. The line was extended further south to Groton, Connecticut, in 1899. Throughout the 20th century the former N&W line was used as a major exchange route with the Boston & Maine Railroad in shipping goods to northern New England. In 1969 the New Haven Railroad merged into Penn Central. In 1976 the resurrected Providence & Worcester Railroad acquired the portion of the N&W between Worcester, Massachusetts, and Plainfield, Connecticut; the remainder of the line, from Plainfield to Groton, Connecticut, came to the P&W in 1980.
The Moshassuck Valley Railroad was an independent 2-mile long short line operated between Lincoln and Pawtucket, Rhode Island, founded in 1877 to serve the textile mills between the two towns. In 1981 it was absorbed by the Providence & Worcester Railroad.
The American Short Line and Regional Railroad Association (ASLRRA), formerly known as the American Short Line Railroad Association, is an association of North American short line and regional railroads. Members include a variety of Class II and Class III railroads. The ASLRRA acts as a lobbying group for member railroads, representing them for both legislation and regulation.
Moshassuck Valley Railroad.; Norwich & Worcester Railroad.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Maps.; Railroads -- Connecticut.; Railroads -- Massachusetts.; Railroads -- Rhode Island.
- Series I: Providence & Worcester Railroad: Old Company, 1845-1962
  - Subseries A: President's Office correspondence and bonds, 1845-1927 (Box 1)
  - Subseries B: Treasurer's Office, 1845-1962
    - Correspondence, 1848-1927
      - 1848-1878 (Box 2)
      - 1878-1893 (Box 3)
      - 1893-1927 (Box 4)
      - 1867-1890 (Box 5)
      - 1891-1899 (Box 6)
      - 1900-1911 (Box 7)
      - 1912-1925 (Box 8)
    - Accounts, 1856-1925
      - 1856-1880 (Box 9)
      - 1881-1892 (Box 10)
      - 1893-1925 (Box 11)
    - Ledger balances, works ledger, expenses ledger, and financial journal, 1846-1919 (Box 12)
    - Balances ledgers, 1891-1919 (Box 13)
    - Cash books, 1845-1962
      - "A", 1845-1849 (Volume 14)
      - "B", 1849-1854 (Volume 15)
      - "C", 1855-1860 (Volume 16)
      - "D", 1860-1863 (Volume 17)
      - "E", 1863-1866 (Volume 18)
      - "F", 1866-1868 (Volume 19)
      - "G", 1868-1870 (Volume 20)
      - "H", 1870-1872 (Volume 21)
      - "I", 1872-1873 (Volume 22)
      - "J", 1873-1875 (Volume 23)
      - "K", 1875-1876 (Volume 24)
      - "L", 1876-1878 (Volume 25)
      - "M", 1878-1880 (Volume 26)
      - "N", 1880-1881 (Volume 27)
      - "O", 1882-1883 (Volume 28)
      - "P", 1883-1885 (Volume 29)
      - "Q", 1885-1887 (Volume 30)
      - "R", 1887-1901 (Volume 31)
      - "S", 1902-1933 (Volume 32)
      - "T", 1934-1962 (Volume 33)
    - Cash balances ledgers, 1886-1927
      - 1886-1888 (Volume 34)
      - 1889-1904 (Volume 35)
      - 1905-1922 (Volume 36)
      - 1921-1927 (Volume 37)
    - Ledger "A" index, 1845-1880 (Volume 38)
    - Ledger "A", 1845-1880 (Volume 39)
    - Ledger "B", 1881-1949 (Volume 40)
    - Journal "C", 1881-1949 (Volume 41)
    - Assessment book, 1845-1847 (Volume 42)
    - Memoranda concerning railroad operations, 1848-1863 (Volume 43)
    - Property accounts ledger, 1848-1878 (Volume 44)
    - Payroll ledger, 1878-1881 (Volume 45)
    - Miscellaneous works ledger, 1879-1884 (Volume 46)
    - Payroll ledger, 1880-1881 (Volume 47)
    - Receipts and new stock issues, 1881 (Volume 48)
    - Index to stock ledger "A", 1847 (Volume 49)
    - Stock ledger "A", 1847-1884 (Volume 50)
    - Stock ledger "B", 1884-1901 (Volume 51)
    - Lists of stockholders, 1847-1848, 1886, 1889, 1920s, 1942
      - 1847-1848, 1920s (Box 119)
        Scope and Content Note
        Includes dividends of interest.
      - 1886 (Volume 117)
      - 1889 (Volume 118)
      - 1942 (Box 116)
    - Dividends ledgers, 1850-1921
      - "A", 1850-1859 (Volume 52)
      - "B", 1860-1867 (Volume 53)
      - "C", 1867-1873 (Volume 54)
      - "D", 1874-1880 (Volume 55)
      - "E", 1880-1886 (Volume 56)
      - "F", 1886-1888 (Volume 57)
      - "181-192", 1915-1917 (Volume 58)
      - "193-208", 1918-1921 (Volume 59)
    - Correspondence regarding payroll, payroll reports, income tax documents, 1927-1960 (Box 65)
    - Corporation income and excess profits tax documents and tax correspondence, 1943-1962 (Box 66)
  - Subseries C: Superintendent's Office, 1848-1888
    - Letters, 1848-1888
      - 1848-1859 (Box 60)
      - 1860-1869 (Box 61)
      - 1869-1880 (Box 62)
      - 1880-1888 (Box 63)
    - Reports to the directors, 1848-1864 (Box 64)
- Series II: Providence & Worcester Railroad: New Company, 1935-1982
  - Financial documents, 1955-1981
    - Stockholder's documents, application for permission to operate independently, annual report, prospectus, minutes, 1955-1981 (Box 67)
    - Stock transfer journals, 1975-1981 (Box 68)
- Series III: Norwich & Worcester Railroad, 1832-1997
  - Subseries A: President's Office (documents include charters, acts to incorporate and for railroad construction, deeds, bonds and mortgages), 1845-1897 (Box 72)
  - Subseries B: Stockholder reports and correspondence, capital stock documents and directors correspondence, 1836-1897 (Box 73)
  - Subseries C: General documents, 1841-1970
    - Accidents, agreements, insurance, patents, real estate, correspondence with other railroads, steamboat agreements (including "City of Lowell"), taxes, telegraph and telephone service, and provision of water, 1841-1922 (Box 74)
    - Record of contents in vault, by-laws, mortgages, balance sheets, and authority for expenditure records, 1897-1970 (Box 75)
- Series IV: Moshassuck Valley Railroad, 1874-1962
  - Financial documents, 1874-1962
    - Agreements, tax returns and income tax documents, and correspondence, 1874-1933 (Box 76)
    - Income tax returns, insurance, and agreements with other companies, 1881-1962 (Box 77)
- Series V: American Short Line Railroad Association, 1968-1971 (Box 69)
  [annual meeting proceedings, newsletters, correspondence and traffic bulletins]
- Series VI: Real Estate documents (all railroads in the collection), 1826-1968
  - Subseries A: Connecticut, undated, 1826-1980
    - Chaplin, East Hampton, Ellington, Hampton, Lisbon, Manchester, Pomfret, Vernon, Willimantic, and Windsor Locks, 1963-1980 (Box 70)
    - Groton extension in Groton and Ledyard, 1898-1952 (Box 81)
    - Ledyard, Preston and Norwich, 1826-1957 (Box 82)
    - Norwich, 1836-1958 (Box 83)
    - Lisbon, Griswold, and Plainfield, 1836-1974 (Box 84)
    - Killingly and Thompson, undated, 1838-1974 (Box 85)
  - Subseries B: Massachusetts, undated, 1838-1982
    - Allston, Blackstone, Stoughton, Westwood and Worcester) and Rhode Island ( Bristol, East Providence, Pawtucket, Providence, Warren, and Warwick), 1935-1982 (Box 71)
    - Webster, Oxford and Auburn, undated, 1838-1958 (Box 86)
    - Worcester, 1832-1959
      - 1832-1951 (Box 87)
      - 1832-1959 (Box 88)
    - Attleboro, Blackstone, Bourne, Fall River, and Seekonk, 1835-1959 (Box 89)
  - Subseries C: Rhode Island, undated, 1835-1981
    - Lincoln and Pawtucket, 1839-1981
      - 1878-1967 (Box 78)
      - 1839-1880, 1981 (Box 79)
    - Bellingham, Coventry, and Cranston, 1852-1964 (Box 90)
    - Cumberland and East Providence, undated, 1836-1965 (Box 91)
    - East Providence, Lincoln, North Smithfield, and Pawtucket, 1835-1962 (Box 92)
    - Providence, 1836-1967
      - 1836-1960 (Box 93)
      - 1837-1967 (Box 94)
    - Tiverton, Warwick, and Woonsocket, 1852-1968 (Box 95)
    - Barrington, Bristol, East Providence, and Warren, 1854-1959 (Box 97)
    - Inventory booklets for property in Rhode Island, 1915-1918 (Box 98)
  - Subseries D: Other documents, undated, 1915-1977
    - Photocopies of schedules of title from valuation maps of the railroad line through Connecticut, Massachusetts and Rhode Island, 1915 (Box 80)
    - Indexes and conveyances, undated (Box 96)
    - Record of Land Changes for Interstate Commerce Commission, Division of Valuation, Carrier Land in Rhode Island (VS32.50), 1917-1927 (Volume 99)
    - Record of Property Changes for Interstate Commerce Commission, Division of Valuation, Carrier Land in Massachusetts (VS33), 1916-1968
      - 1916-1927 (Volume 110)
      - 1928-1941 (Volume 101)
      - 1928-1944 (Volume 111)
      - 1942-1968 (Volume 100)
    - Joint C, Report to the Interstate Commerce Comission, Massachusetts (VS33.12), 1915-1917 (Volume 102)
    - Reports to the Interstate Commerce Commission, Massachusetts (VS33), 1950-1977 (Volume 103)
    - Reports to the Interstate Commerce Commission, Rhode Island (VS32), 1915-1966
      - 1915-1953 (Volume 105)
      - 1954-1966 (Volume 104)
    - Reports to the Interstate Commerce Commission, Rhode Island (VS33), 1915-1967
      - 1915-1949 (Volume 107)
      - 1950-1967 (Volume 106)
    - Roadway Completion Reports, 1952-1958
      - 1952-1957 (Volume 109)
      - 1952-1958 (Volume 108)
    - Land owned by the Providence & Worcester Railroad, valuation of property in Rhode Island, 1915 (Box 115)
- Series VII: Maps, 1915, 1960-1974
  - 1960-1974 (Box 112)
    [Subjects include: Westerly, Rhode Island; Boston, Massachusetts (South Station floor plans, 1960); Worcester, Massachusetts; Fall River, Massachusetts; easements in Boston, Brookline and Newton, Massachusetts; Old Saybrook, Connecticut]
  - Valuation maps, Worcester, Massachusetts, to Groton, Connecticut, 1915 (Folder 120)